Nicole: What exactly is a cyber
security incident response plan?
A cyber security incident plan consists
of instructions on how to respond to and
recover from network security incidents.
Abraham: Incident plans may be drawn
up to address issues such as malware
detection, data theft and service
outages, but it also should include
all areas as cyber attacks can
affect any part of an organisation.
So, when is a cyber security
incident response plan used?
Nicole: As we have previously mentioned
every organisation whether large or small
should have a Cyber Security Incident
Response Plan or IR and this usually
comes into play when a breach is detected.
It can also help to protect a system
by planning for backups to secure data,
security alerts to detect any malicious
activity and efficient patch management.
Identity and access management should
be used to avoid insider threats.
Abraham: Incident response planning can
protect an organisations reputation by
helping to show that they are prepared.
It can also be a more cost-effective way
of handling cyber security as breaches
can be expensive due to loss of data,
downtime of systems, costs involved with
investigating and restoring systems.
Nicole: Having an incident response
plan is an important part of the
whole cyber security process.
It can help set out the role that
everyone should play and the processes
that should be followed at all
times and not just during an attack.
Abraham: A plan should consist of a
series of actions to follow but should
also provide a checklist approach so
that actions are consistent across
all areas appropriate to the plan.